Chapter 103.
measurement of the whale's skeleton.
In the first place, I wish to lay before you a particular plain statement
touching the living bulk of this Leviathan whose skeleton we are briefly
to exhibit, such a statement may prove useful here.
According to a careful calculation I have made and which I partly base upon
Captain Scoresby's estimate of 70 tons for the largest size Greenland whale of
60 ft in length. According to my careful calculation I say a sperm whale of the
largest magnitude between 85 and 90 ft in length and something less than 40 ft
in its fullest circumference. Such a whale will weigh at least 90 tons. so
that reckoning 13 men to a ton, he would considerably outweigh the combined
population of a whole village of 1,100 inhabitants.
Think you not then that brains like yolked cattle should be put to this
Leviathan to make him at all budge to any landsman's imagination?
Having already in various ways put before you his skull, spout hole, jaw,
teeth, tail, forehead, fins, and diverse other parts, I shall now simply point
out what is most interesting in the general bulk of his unobstructed bones.
But as the colossal skull embraces so very large a proportion of the entire
extent of the skeleton, as it is by far the most complicated part, and as
nothing is to be repeated concerning it in this chapter, you must not fail to
carry it in your mind or under your arm as we proceed. Otherwise, you will not
gain a complete notion of the general structure we are about to view.
In length, the sperm whale's skeleton at tran measured 72 feet, so that when
fully invested and extended in life, he must have been 90 feet long. For in the
whale, the skeleton loses about 1/5th in length compared with the living body. Of
this 72 ft, his skull and jaw comprised some 20 ft, leaving some 50 ft of plain
backbone. Attached to this backbone, for something less than a third of its
length, was the mighty circular basket of ribs which once enclosed his vitals.
To me this vast ivory ribbed chest with the long unreieved spine extending far
away from it in a straight line not a little resembled the hull of a great
ship new laid upon the stocks when only some 20 of her naked bow ribs are
inserted and the keel is otherwise for the time but a long disconnected timber.
The ribs were 10 on a side. The first to begin from the neck was nearly six feet
long. The second, third, and fourth were each successively longer till you came
to the climax of the fifth or one of the middle ribs, which measured 8 ft and
some inches. From that part, the remaining ribs diminished, till the 10th
and last only spanned 5 ft and some inches. In general thickness, they all
bore a seemly correspondence to their length. The middle ribs were the most
arched. In some of the arcs, they are used for beams whereon to lay footpath
bridges over small streams.
In considering these ribs, I could not but be struck a new with the
circumstance so variously repeated in this book that the skeleton of the whale
is by no means the mold of his invested form. The largest of the tran ribs, one
of the middle ones, occupied that part of the fish, which in life is greatest
in depth. Now, the greatest depth of the invested body of this particular whale
must have been at least 16 ft, whereas the corresponding rib measured but
little more than 8 ft, so that this rib only conveyed half of the true notion of
the living magnitude of that part.
Besides, for some way, where I now saw but a naked spine, all that had been
once wrapped round with tons of added bulk in flesh, muscle, blood, and
bowels, still more, for the ample fins, I here saw but a few disordered joints,
and in place of the weighty and majestic but boneless flukes, an utter blank.
How vain and foolish then, thought I, for timid, untraveled man to try to
comprehend a right this wondrous whale by merely pouring over his dead
attenuated skeleton stretched in this peaceful wood. No, only in the heart of
quickest perils, only when within the eddings of his angry flukes, only on the
profound unbounded sea can the fully invested whale be truly and livingly
found out. But the spine, for that the best way we can consider it is with a
crane to pile its bones high up on end.
No speedy enterprise. But now it's done, it looks much like Pompy's pillar. There
are 40 and odd vertebrae in all, which in the skeleton are not locked together.
They mostly lie like the great knobbed blocks on a Gothic spire, forming solid
courses of heavy masonry. The largest, a middle one, is in width something less
than 3 ft and in depth more than four.
The smallest, where the spine tapers away into the tail, is only 2 in in
width and looks something like a white billiard ball. I was told that there
were still smaller ones, but that they had been lost by some little cannibal
urchins, the priest's children, who had stolen them to play marbles with. Thus
we see how that the spine of even the hugest of living things tapers off at
last into simple child's play.